You may have heard
the expression
“knowledge is power.”
Well, today we’re going
to give you more power
to control your
diet and lifestyle
by giving you the facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we look
at the safety
of fourth generation
sweeteners
such as the rare
sugar allulose.
First there was sugar and
high fructose corn syrup,
the original industrial sweeteners.
They were cheap, but had
lots of empty calories,
and contributed to diseases
such as obesity, type 2 diabetes,
cavities, and metabolic syndrome.
So then came the second-generation
sweeteners, the artificial sweeteners,
the colored pastel packets:
Nutrasweet, Splenda,
Sweet & Low.
Practically zero calories,
but adverse effects have been
described, cautions have been raised.
For example, artificial sweeteners were
found to induce glucose intolerance
by altering the gut microbiome,
thereby producing
the counterintuitive effect of
inducing metabolic derangements.
They also taste kind of funny.
Enter the third-generation
Sweeteners, sugar alcohols,
such as sorbitol, xylitol, and
erythritol, low-calorie sweeteners,
however, their laxative effects
can create difficulties,
which brings us to rare sugars
like allulose, which are
natural sweeteners with low or
zero calories and a sugar-like taste.
For those of you who
haven't heard of allulose,
it's been through
a bit of rebranding.
Just like rapeseed oil morphed
into canola, forcing municipalities
to update their town slogans,
allulose used to be called psicose,
a sugar you may not want to eat
in the shower.
The name "psicose" is derived
from the antibiotic from which
it was isolated --- a strange
origin story for a sweetener.
In the Frontiers of Bioengineering
and Biotechnology, emphasis
is placed on the fact that
allulose is a real and natural sugar
rather than artificial, but ironically
if you look at a reference they cite,
it talks about how allulose
is made, via functionalized
polyhydroxyalkanoate nano-beads
decorated with D-tagatose
3-epimerase (DTE)
produced in recombinant
endotoxin-free branded bacteria.
And now technically allulose is a
natural sugar, a so-called rare sugar,
which have been defined by the
International Society of Rare Sugars
as sugars that are present
in limited quantities in nature.
But recent technological advances,
such as enzymatic engineering
using genetically modified
microorganisms, now allow
manufacturers to produce
otherwise rare sugars
like allulose in
substantial quantities.
But small amounts have
pre-existed in the food supply,
so the FDA granted it generally
recognized as safe status,
but it's been like really
small amounts, like a few
dozen milligrams, or a quarter of
a quarter of a quarter of a teaspoon.
See, allulose is generated
when fructose is heated.
And allulose is
created incidentally
in the process by which high
fructose corn syrup is made.
So basing the safety of allulose
on the fact that it's already been
present in the food supply
isn't very convincing.
You don't know if it's safe
until you put it to the test.
Unlike table sugar, allulose
is safe for the teeth;
isn't apparently metabolized
by cavity-causing bacteria
to make acid and
build up plaque.
It doesn't raise blood sugars,
even in diabetics.
It can be labeled as having
zero calories, though technically
it may have like one and a half
calories per teaspoon,
similar to what you
see with erythritol.
Also like erythritol, it's only about
70% as sweet as table sugar
but has almost the same
taste, performance,
and texture as regular sugar.
Are there any toxicities?
Allulose is considered
a relatively nontoxic sugar.
What does that mean?
Well, in pets, we know a
sweetener called xylitol can
be extremely dangerous to dogs.
As little as a half teaspoon in a
30-pound dog can be life-threatening,
whereas a similar dose of allulose
apparently wouldn't be a problem,
though like over half cup at
a time could make them sick.
This was a single dose
study though.
The long-term safety of allulose
was tested over a period
of a few months and didn't seem to
cause any harmful effects at a dose
of about one and a half teaspoons
a day for healthy 30-pound dogs.
In fact, their cholesterol
actually went down,
leading the investigators
to suggest clinical studies to see
if it's something vets should start
prescribing for overweight pooches.
What about in people?
When the dose of allulose
was gradually increased
to identify the maximum single
dose for occasional ingestion,
no cases of severe gastrointestinal
symptoms were noted
until a dose of 0.4 g/kg of
bodyweight was reached,
which could be about 7 teaspoons,
with severe symptoms
of diarrhea noted once you
get up around 9 teaspoons.
And you say, "who could eat that
much sugar at a time anyway?"
A single can of Coke
has 10 teaspoons,
and a bottle of Mountain Dew
has nearly twice that.
So allulose is clearly not suitable
as a standalone sweetener
for sugary beverages.
In terms of the daily upper limit
given in smaller doses
throughout the day, once you
hit around 17 teaspoons a day,
depending on your weight,
people start getting
severe nausea, abdominal
pain, headache, diarrhea.
So people should probably
stay under single doses
of about 7 teaspoons,
and not exceed around
15 for the whole day.
The average American may
be getting 17 teaspoons
of added sugar a day,
so it's certainly not something
the food industry can
completely switch over to.
In this way, allulose is close
to xylitol in terms of
maximal single dose,
whereas the average-weight man
in the US could get away with
14 teaspoons of
erythritol at a time,
and the average woman,
15 teaspoons.
Still not enough to sweeten
a bottle of Coke, but offers
a little more leeway
for sweetening tea
or sprinkling on a
grapefruit or something.
Allulose is claimed to
provide health benefits
though, compared to erythritol.
Forth generation sweeteners
like allulose are said to have
as an advantage:
additional functions.
We'll find out if that's true, next.
Allulose is a kind of low-calorie
sugar naturally existing
in very small quantities,
but now industrially produced
as a commercial sweetener,
said to have advantages
that make it comparable to
erythritol as a sugar substitute.
It's said to have
anti-diabetic effects,
but this was in obese mice.
Allulose decreases LDL cholesterol
levels in high fat-fed hamsters and
is said to have a substantial impact
on obesity in lard-munching mice,
but what about men and women?
In a petri dish, allulose
inhibits fat cell precursors
from maturing into fat cells
and reduced the amount of
fat accumulation within fat cells.
Therefore, the researchers
conclude, allulose may be
a promising sugar substitute
for an anti-obesity diet,
but you don't know
until you put it to the test.
They gave people about a
teaspoon of allulose a half hour
before eating a meal, and compared
to the no-sugar control group,
the allulose group started
burning more fat.
The researchers concluded
that allulose enhances
after-a-meal fat burning,
indicating that it could be
a novel sweetener
to control and maintain
healthy body weight through
enhanced energy metabolism.
Okay, but first of all,
it was only 15 calories of fat
burned over that 4-hour period.
And they didn't burn
more calories overall.
They just switched from burning
carb calories to fat calories
and so may have just switched
back later on and made up
for it later in the day. You
can't just look at one meal.
You need to track people's actual
weight over time, and here we go.
A weight reducing effect of a syrup
that included about 5% allulose,
compared to high fructose corn syrup.
The results show significant
decreases in body weight, body fat,
and waist circumference, but it was
some proprietary syrup mixture,
and look, anything would look good
against high fructose corn syrup.
This is the study
I've been looking for.
Evaluating the effect of allulose
for fat mass reduction in humans.
Over a hundred individuals
randomized to a placebo
control -- sucralose --
or a teaspoon of allulose
twice a day,
or one-and-three-quarter
teaspoons twice a day,
and despite no change
of physical activity
or calorie consumption
between the two groups,
body fat was significantly decreased
following allulose supplementation.
They even took CT scans,
so they could tell where
the fat was disappearing from.
Now, the drop in body fat was only
about 2 pounds over 12 weeks,
and the drop in abdominal fat
in the higher dose group
was almost totally a drop
in subcutaneous fat,
the flabby superficial fat,
not the dangerous visceral fat
deeper down that
really matters for health.
But still, a body fat loss despite
no change in calorie intake,
similar to what was
seen in the mice,
but the hamster effect
did not materialize:
no significant change in LDL
cholesterol in either
of the allulose groups.
What about the purported
anti-diabetes effects?
If you have people chug a beverage
with up to about 2 teaspoons
of allulose alone -- previously
known as psicose -- or with
a big load of rapidly-digesting carbs,
the allulose alone has predictably
no influence on blood glucose
or insulin concentration.
Yet when you consume allulose
along with the refined carbs,
there is actually a suppression of the
elevation of blood sugar and insulin,
and by a significant amount: a 30%
drop in blood sugar and insulin levels
over a two-hour period. We think it's
because the presence of allulose
impairs the absorption of sugar
through the intestinal lining,
because they all might be competing
for the same sugar transporter.
Yeah, but who's chugging maltodextrin?
What about just like a regular meal?
And here we go -- and
in borderline diabetics
who could use some blood
sugar spike suppression.
A randomized double-blind placebo-
controlled crossover experiment
to see what drinking one and
a quarter teaspoon of allulose
in a cup of tea
with a meal would do,
and indeed a significant drop,
though only about 15%.
You can see how they
tried to exaggerate the y-axis.
They also did a second experiment:
randomized people to a little over
a teaspoon of allulose three times
a day with meals for 12 weeks.
Nice to see there didn't appear
to be any adverse side effects,
but they also didn't find
any weight loss effects,
in contrast with that other study.
So the body fat data [are] mixed
and so too [are] the sugar data.
This study found no effects
of allulose on blood sugars
in healthy participants, though
a similar study on diabetics did.
A systematic review and meta-analysis
of all such controlled feeding trials
suggest that the acute
benefits on blood sugars
was of borderline significance,
and it's unclear whether or
not this alone could translate
into meaningful improvements
in blood sugar control over time,
so maybe it's not enough
to just add allulose.
You might actually have
to also cut out the junk.
Although ability to suppress
blood sugar responses
is the most well studied
aspect of allulose, I do just want
to cover one last angle:
the fact that allulose extends
the lifespan of a tiny roundworm
called "C. elegans" through
a dietary restriction mechanism,
even though they ate
the same amount of food.
Two months in, just a few percent
of the control group were still alive,
whereas twice as many
in the low allulose group
and about 25% still around
in the higher allulose group.
We think it worked boosting
the expression and activities
of antioxidant enzymes
in the body,
extending lifespan by
mopping up free radicals.
But who cares about the
survival curves of worms?
Well, C. elegans is a well-studied
model of aging and longevity,
but mostly just for convenience sake,
but does share most of the longevity
genes or pathways we're interested in.
It would be nice to see experiments on
at least human cells, and here we go.
The effect of allulose on free
radicals and oxidative stress
in human coronary artery
endothelial cells --
the cells that line the
inside of our arteries.
Add a bunch of sugar, and
free radical levels shoot up,
but add the same amount of sugar
along with some allulose,
and it's as if you never
even added the sugar,
and this then translates
to inhibiting the expression
of an inflammatory marker
that plays a role in the buildup
of atherosclerotic plaque.
However, it's still too
early to draw conclusions
about the clinical relevance
of these data. To conclude,
are these rare sugars like
allulose healthy alternatives
for traditional sweeteners?
Well, considering the variety
of potentially beneficial
effects of allulose
without known disadvantages from
metabolic and toxicological studies,
allulose may currently be the
most promising rare sugar,
but how much is that saying?
We just don't have
a lot of good human data.
As a result of the absence
of these studies,
it may be too early to recommend
rare sugars for human consumption.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.